A Guide to the Record Group Vertical Files, 1960s-present
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
- Record Group 35 - Outreach and International Affairs
  - RG 35/1 - International Affairs
    - RG 35/1/3 - Steger Center for International Scholarship
      The Center for European Studies and Architecture (CESA) [RG 14/7] was founded in 1992. The center was also called the European Studies Center. In 2014, it was renamed Steger Center for International Scholarship.
      See also RG 14/7.
    - RG 35/1/4 - International Support Services
    - RG 35/1/5a - Virginia Tech, India
      May include Virginia Tech-MARG Swarnabhoomi, India; Postgraduate Program in Business Analytics; Kalinga Institute
  - RG 35/2 - Engagement
    May include Virginia Tech Southwest Center; Engagement Scholarship Consortium
  - RG 35/3 - The Inn at Virginia Tech and Skelton Conference Center
    May include The Parents Club; Preston's Restaurant
    See also RG 6/3/2b for the building.
  - RG 35/4 - Continuing and Professional Education
    The Division of Continuing Education was created in 1968 as part of the Virginia Cooperative Extension [RG 26/3]. It oversaw the Continuing Education Center (CEC), later renamed the Donaldson Brown Center for Continuing Education, the Donaldson Brown Hotel and Conference Center, and Graduate Life Center at Donaldson Brown (GLC). The Division moved to Outreach and International Affairs in 1990 and was renamed Continuing and Professional Education [RG 35/4].
    May include Lifelong Learning Institute at Virginia Tech; Lake Lugano Chamber Music Festival; Continuing Education; Outreach Program Development; Virginia Tech Creative Learning Academy for Senior Scholars (VT CLASS)
    See also RG 26/3.
  - RG 35/5 - Economic Development
    May include Catalyst Program; Vibrant Virginia; Rural Virginia Initiative
  - RG 35/6 - Catawba Sustainability Center
  - RG 35/7 - Virginia Tech Language and Culture Institute (LCI)
    May include Hubert H. Humphrey Fellowship Program; Effat University partnership; Friends of Fulbright Argentina Undergraduate Student Exchange Program; AdvantageVT Pathway Program
  - RG 35/8 - Virginia Tech Roanoke Center
    May include VT EarthWorks; Roanoke Regional Inititiatives; Science Museum of Western Virginia partnership
  - RG 35/9 - Virginia Tech Richmond Center
  - RG 35/10 - Reynolds Homestead
- Record Group 36 - Visiting Scholars Programs
  - RG 36 - Visiting Scholar Programs (Information)
  - RG 36 - Visiting Scholar Programs (Brochures)
- Record Group 37 - Center for Public Administration and Policy
  The Center for Public Administration and Public Affairs was renamed Center for Public Administration and Policy. It is housed in the School of Public and International Affairs [RG 14/12] in the College of Architecture and Urban Studies [RG 14].
  May include Graduate Certificate in Local Government Management Program
  See also RG 14/12.
  - RG 37 - Center for Public Administration and Policy (Information and Publications)
- Record Group 38 - Center for Interdisciplinary Programs
  May include Curriculum Transformation Project
  See also RG 15/27.
  - RG 38 - Interdisciplinary Programs (Information)
  - RG 38/1 - Virginia Tech Museum of Natural History [obsolete, 2004] [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    A branch of the Virginia Museum of Natural History, the Virginia Tech Museum of Natural History opened in April 1990 on the Blacksburg campus of Virginia Tech. In July 1991, it absorbed the Virginia Tech Center for Systematic Collections [RG 25/6], which was influential in bringing the branch to fruition, and combined the many natural history collections throughout campus. The branch closed in 2004.
  - RG 38/2 - Powell River Project
  - RG 38/3 - Satellite Enrichment Program (High School)
  - RG 38/4 - Center for Transport Theory and Mathematical Physics
- Record Group 39 - Centers
  May include Center for Regional Strategies
  - RG 39 - Centers (Information and Publications)
  - RG 39/1 - Center for Programs in the Humanities
    May include Choices and Challenges Forum [see also RG 15/27/1]; Appalachian Studies [see RG 42]
    See also RG 15/17; RG 15/17/1; RG 42.
  - RG 39/2 - Center for Housing Research
  - RG 39/3 - Virginia Tech Transportation Institute (VTTI) [obsolete; see RG 25/20]
  - RG 39/4 - Women's Research Institute
  - RG 39/5 - Urban Pest Control Research Center
  - RG 39/6 - Laboratory for Neurotoxicity Studies
  - RG 39/7 - Center for Commercial Space Committees
  - RG 39/8 - Economic Development Assistance Center
  - RG 39/9 - National Science Foundation (NSF) Science and Technology Center
  - RG 39/10 - Center for Excellence in Teaching and Learning
    The Center for Instructional Development and Educational Research (CIDER) was called the Center for Excellence in Undergraduate Teaching (CEUT) until 2009. In 2018, CIDER was renamed Center for Excellence in Teaching and Learning.
    May include Exemplary Department of Program Award; Scholarship of Teaching and Learning Award; Conference on Higher Education Pedagogy; Conference on Teaching Large Classes
  - RG 39/11 - National Center for Research in Vocational Education (NCRVE)
  - RG 39/12 - Center for Active Retirement (C-FAR)
  - RG 39/13 - Center for Rural Development
  - RG 39/14 - Waste Policy Institute
  - RG 39/15 - Community Design Assistance Center
  - RG 39/16 - Center for Survey Research
  - RG 39/17 - Career Development Center (Northern Virginia Campus)
  - RG 39/18 - Center for Research in Health Behavior
  - RG 39/19 - Center for Infrastructure Assessment and Management (CIAM)
  - RG 39/20 - Center for Organizational and Technological Advancement (COTA)
    May include Healthcare Coaching Institute
  - RG 39/21 - Southwest Virginia Higher Education Center
  - RG 39/22 - Advanced Communications and Information Technology Center
    May include Cave Automatic Virtual Environment (CAVE)
  - RG 39/23 - Center for Applied Behavior Systems
  - RG 39/24 - Hampton Roads Center for Continuing Higher Education and Graduate School
  - RG 39/25 - Roanoke Higher Education Center
    See also RG 35/8.
  - RG 39/26 - Carilion Biomedical Institute [obsoleted; see RG 46]
- Record Group 40 - University History
  May include Camp Humphries; Camp Lee; Coatee; Collegians (Dance Orchestra); "Firsts" at VPI; Students' Army Training Corps, World War I (WWI); Techlore; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College (VAMC); Virginia Tech Commemorative Coin (unofficial?); Iron Worker
  - RG 40 - University History (Information and Publications) [items also in Oversize Box 2]
  - RG 40/1 - Gobbler and Hokie
    See also RG 10/11a.
  - RG 40/2 - Land Grant
    May include Morrill Act
    - RG 40/2a - Centennial Anniversary, 1962
    - RG 40/2b - 125th Anniversary, 1987 [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    - RG 40/2c - 150th Anniversary, 2012
  - RG 40/3 - University Seals and Logos
    See also RG 21/3 for university branding and trademarks.
  - RG 40/4 - History
    - RG 40/4a - Coofer
    - RG 40/4b - House and Senate Bills (Virginia General Assembly)
  - RG 40/5 - Colors
  - RG 40/6 - Newspaper Clippings with Index
    - RG 40/6a - Newspaper Clippings, 1913
    - RG 40/6b - Newspaper Clippings, 1914
    - RG 40/6c - Newspaper Clippings, 1915
    - RG 40/6d - Newspaper Clippings, 1916
    - RG 40/6e - Newspaper Clippings, 1917
    - RG 40/6f - Newspaper Clippings, 1918
    - RG 40/6g - Newspaper Clippings, 1919-1922
    - RG 40/6h - Newspaper Clippings, 1923-1924
    - RG 40/6i - Newspaper Clippings, 1925-1926
    - RG 40/6j - Newspaper Clippings, 1927-1928
    - RG 40/6k - Newspaper Clippings, 1910s-1920s, undated
  - RG 40/7 - Newspaper Clippings without Index, 1879-1980, 1910
  - RG 40/8 - University Songs
    May include Alma Mater; Songs of VPI; Moonlight and VPI; Tech Triumph; Ut Prosim; Dance bands
    See also RG 15/15/2c for Songs of VPI.
  - RG 40/10 - History of Women
    May include 75th Anniversary of Women Students at Virginia Tech
- Record Group 41 - Center for Innovative Technology
  In 1984, the Virginia General Assembly created Virginia's Center for Innovative Technology, which established Technology Development Centers (TDCs) at universities across Virginia. TDCs established at Virginia Tech include Fiber and Electro-Optics Research Center [RG 18/6/1], Virginia Power Electronics Center [RG 18/6/2], Center for Coal and Minerals Processing, Center for Advanced Ceramic Materials, Center for Biobased Materials [RG 13/18], Center for Wireless Telecommunications, and Internet Technology Innovation Center.
  May include Center for Information Retrieval, Analysis, and Management (IRAM)
  See also RG 13/18; RG 18/6/1; RG 18/6/2.
- Record Group 42 - Appalachian Studies [obsolete]
  Appalachian Studies was part of the Center for Interdisciplinary Studies [RG 15/27; RG 38] and Center for Programs in the Humanities [RG 39/1]. Later, it merged into the Department of Religion and Culture [RG 48/6].
  See also RG 15/27; RG 38; RG 48/6.
  - RG 42 - Appalachian Studies (Information and Publications) [obsolete] [items also in Oversize Box 2]
- Record Group 43 - Woodrow Wilson College
- Record Group 44 - Hotel Roanoke & Conference Center
  The Hotel Roanoke was built in 1882 by Norfolk and Western Railway. In 1989, the Railway donated the hotel to the university's Division of Continuing Education [RG 35/4] in what later became Outreach and International Affairs [RG 35]. After extensive renovations and a new conference center, the hotel reopened in 1995.
  See also RG 35/8; Hotel Roanoke in the Southwest Virginia Vertical Files.
- Record Group 45 - College of Natural Resources and Environment (CNRE)
  By the 1930s, Virginia Polytechnic Institute offered its first programs in forestry and wildlife. The Virginia Cooperative Wildlife Research Unit began in 1935, and three years later the Department of Biology started offering the first B.S. in conservation and forestry. In 1959, the Department of Forestry and Wildlife was founded in the College of Agriculture. In 1974, the Department split into the departments of Forestry and Forest Products and of Fisheries and Wildlife Sciences. A year later, the School of Forestry and Wildlife Resources was created within the College of Agriculture.
  By 1992, the College of Forestry and Wildlife Resources was established, offering majors and minors to students, although it was not fully phased in until 1994. In 2000, the college changed its name to the College of Natural Resources, and in 2010, it became the College of Natural Resources and Environment.
  - RG 45 - College of Natural Resources and Environment (CNRE) (Information and Publications) [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    May include Conservation Management Institute [see also RG 45/3]; Sustainability Institute; Center for Geospatial Information Technology; Center for Environmental Analytics and Remote Sensing (CEARS); Office of Geographic Information Systems and Remote Sensing Research (OGIS); Center for Leadership in Global Sustainability; Galway-Mayo Institute of Technology (GMIT) partnership
  - RG 45/1 - Office of the Dean
  - RG 45/2 - Individual Faculty
  - RG 45/3 - Department of Fish and Wildlife Conservation [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    The Department of Fisheries and Wildlife Sciences was renamed the Department of Fish and Wildlife Conservation in 2011.
    May include Stroubles Creek Restoration Initiative; Conservation Management Institute [see also RG 45]; Bear Research Center; Fish and Wildlife Graduate Student Association
  - RG 45/4 - Department of Sustainable Biomaterials
    The Department of Wood Science and Forest Products was renamed the Department of Sustainable Biomaterials in 2012.
    May include Wood Enterprise Institute; Thomas M. Brooks Forest Products Center; Center for Packaging and Unit Load Design; Sloan Foundation Forest Industries Center
  - RG 45/5 - Department of Forest Resources and Environmental Conservation
    The Department of Foresty was renamed the Department of Forest Resources and Environmental Conservation in 2009.
    May include Virginia Geospatial Extension Program; Virginia Big Tree Program; Water: Resources, Policy, and Management degree; Virginia Forest Landowner Education Program; Forestry
  - RG 45/6 - Cooperative Fisheries Research Unit
  - RG 45/7 - Cooperative Wildlife Research Unit
  - RG 45/9 - Aquaculture Research Facility (Fisheries)
  - RG 45/10 - Department of Geography
    Courses in geography were offered as early as 1872. Prior to 1973, geography classes were offered through Courses in General Arts and Sciences. In 1973, a Program in Geography was offered through the College of Arts and Sciences (CAS). The Geography Department was established in 1978. The department moved from CAS [RG 15/20] to the College of Natural Resources and Environment (CNRE) in 2003.
    May include Hokie Storm Chase Crew; Meteorology
    See also RG 15/20.
- Record Group 46 - Virginia Tech Carilion (VTC)
  Collectively called Virginia Tech Carilion (VTC), the Virginia Tech Carilion School of Medicine and Research Institute was announced in January 2007 as a public-private partnership between Virginia Tech and Carilion Clinic in Roanoke, Virginia. The Virginia Tech Carilion School of Medicine (VTCSOM) was established in 2010 and became an official college of the university on July 1, 2018. The Virginia Tech Carilion Research Institute (VTCRI) opened on September 1, 2010, and in December 2018, the institute was renamed the Fralin Biomedical Research Institute.
  - RG 46 - Virginia Tech Carilion (VTC) (Information and Publications)
    May include Office of the Vice President for Health Sciences and Technology [see also RG 46b]; Healthstorian (oral history program); VTC Health Sciences and Technology Campus; Integrated Translational Health Research Institute of Virginia (iTHRIV)
  - RG 46a - Seminars, Guest Speakers, Conferences, Programs
    May include Mini Medical School; Oral Health Week
  - RG 46b - Vice President for Health Sciences and Technology
    The Vice President for Health Sciences and Technology was established in March 2016.
  - RG 46/1 - Office of the Dean
    May include Dean's Council on Advancement
    - RG 46/1/1 - Cynda Johnson, 2008-2018
    - RG 46/1/2 - Daniel Harrington, interim, 2019-present
    - RG 46/1/3 - Lee Learman, 2019-present
  - RG 46/2 - Individual Faculty
    May include Outstanding Research Mentor
  - RG 46/3 - Virginia Tech Carilion School of Medicine (VTCSOM)
    Announced in January 2007, the Virginia Tech Carilion School of Medicine (VTCSOM) in Roanoke, Virginia, was established in 2010 and became an official college of the university on July 1, 2018.
    May include Docs for Morgan; Morgan Dana Harrington Memorial Scholarship Fund; Match Day
    - RG 46/3a - Individual Students and Student Research
  - RG 46/4 - Fralin Biomedical Research Institute
    Announced in January 2007, the Virginia Tech Carilion Research Institute (VTCRI) opened on September 1, 2010. In December 2018, the institute was renamed the Fralin Biomedical Research Institute.
    May include Developmental and Translational Neurobiology Center; University of Virginia-Virginia Tech Neuroscience Research Collaboration; Brain Awareness Week; Center for Transformative Research on Health Behaviors; Health Sciences and Technology Commercialization Fellows; Maury Strauss Distinguished Public Lecture Series
  - RG 46/5 - Translational Biology, Medicine, and Health Program
    May include Eric Shullman Distinguished Public Lecture Series
  - RG 46/6 - Department of Biomedical Science
  - RG 46/7 - Department of Surgery
  - RG 46/8 - Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Medicine
  - RG 46/9 - Department of Pediatrics
  - RG 46/10 - Department of Basic Science Education
- Record Group 47 - College of Science
  The College of Science formed from most of the science departments of the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15] when it dissolved in July 2003.
  Although the College of Science was created in 2003, items dated up to 2015 and later may be found in the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15].
  - RG 47 - College of Science (Information and Publications)
    May include Molecular Sciences Software Institute; J. Mark Sowers Distinguished Lecture Series; Hall of Distinction; NanoCamp; Molecular and Cellular Biology program; Science Olympiad; University of Richmond's T. C. Williams School of Law partnership
  - RG 47/1 - Office of the Dean
    - RG 47/1/2 - Sally C. Morton, 2016-present
  - RG 47/2 - Individual Faculty
  - RG 47/3 - Department of Geosciences
    The first degree in Geology was given in 1910. Courses in the geological sciences have been offered under the following departments: Chemistry, Geology, and Mineralogy, 1887-1991; General Chemistry, Mineralogy, and Geology, 1891-1901; Mineralogy, 1901-1902; Geology, Mineralogy, and Organic Chemistry, 1902-1903; Geology and Mineralogy, 1903-1907; Applied Geology, 1907-1920; Geology, 1920-1955; and Geological Sciences, beginning 1955. The department was later renamed the Department of Geosciences. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15/12] to the College of Science in 2003.
    May include Paleobiology; Geobiology; Museum of Geosciences; Paleontology
    See also RG 15/12.
  - RG 47/4 - Department of Physics [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    Physics courses have been offered in some form since 1872. The Department of Physics and Mechanics was formed in 1883, followed by Physics and Electrical Engineering in 1891, Mathematics and Physics in 1898, and Physics in 1904. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15/9] to the College of Science in 2003.
    May include Center for Soft Matter and Biological Physics
    See also RG 15/9.
  - RG 47/5 - School of Neuroscience
  - RG 47/6 - Department of Chemistry
    Chemistry courses have been offered since 1872. However, the department has gone through several name and organizational changes: General and Analytical Chemistry, 1873-1883; Chemistry and Metallurgy, 1883-1887; Chemistry, Geology, and Mineralogy, 1887-1891; General Chemistry, Mineralogy, and Geology, 1891-1901; General and Industrial Chemistry, 1901-1902; Geology, Mineralogy, and Organic Chemistry, 1902-1903; General Chemistry, 1903-1904; Chemistry, 1904-1929; Chemistry and Chemical Engineering, 1929-1935; and Chemistry, 1935-present. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15/6] to the College of Science in 2003.
    See also RG 15/6.
  - RG 47/7 - Department of Psychology
    Prior to 1965, psychology courses were offered in the Vocational Education Department [RG 17/6]. The Department of Psychology and Sociology was formed in 1965, but the departments separated into the Department of Psychology [RG 15/17] and Department of Sociology [RG 15/19] in 1968. The department moved from College of Arts and Sciences to College of Science in 2003.
    May include Social Clinical Affective Neuroscience Lab; Child Study Center
    See also RG 15/17.
  - RG 47/8 - Department of Biological Sciences
    Biology courses have been offered at Virginia Tech since its beginning in 1872. In 1891, the Biology Department was formed. The department was divided into the departments of Botany and Plant Pathology and of Zoology and Animal Pathology in 1926. In 1935, the department was united again as the Biology Department. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15/5] to the College of Science as the Department of Biological Sciences in 2003.
    May include Massey Herbarium; VT-STEM
    See also RG 15/5.
  - RG 47/9 - Department of Statistics
    From 1946 to 1949, courses in statistics were taught as part of the Department of Agriculture Economics, Rural Sociology, and Statistics, which later became the Department of Agricultural and Applied Economics [RG 13/3]. In 1949, the Department of Statistics was formed. The first bachelors degree in statistics was awarded in 1948. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15/18] to the College of Sciencein 2003.
    See also RG 15/18.
  - RG 47/10 - Virginia Tech Center for Drug Discovery
  - RG 47/11 - Department of Economics
    Courses in economics have been offered under a variety of different names since at least 1904: English and Economics, 1904-1905; History and Economics, 1905-1916; Economics and Political Science, 1916-1917; Economics and History, 1924-1957; and a curriculum in Business Administration Department, 1957-1961. The Department of Economics was one of the founding departments within the College of Business [RG 16/5] when it formed in 1961. In 1989, the department moved to the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15/8]. When the college dissolved in 2003, the Department of Economics became one of the founding departments within the College of Science.
    See also RG 15/8; RG 16/5.
  - RG 47/12 - Virginia Tech Center for Autism Research
    May include Mobile Autism Clinic
  - RG 47/13 - Department of Mathematics
    Mathematics courses have been offered since 1872 under different names and organizations of the department: Mathematics, 1872-1891; Mathematics and Civil Engineering, 1891-1894; Mathematics, 1894-1897; Mathematics and Physics, 1897-1904; and Mathematics, 1904-present. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15/14] to the College of Science in 2003.
    See also RG 15/14.
  - RG 47/14 - Academy of Integrated Science
    May include Systems Biology; Nanoscience; Computational Modeling and Data Analytics (CMDA)
- Record Group 48 - College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences (CLAHS)
  The College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences (CLAHS) formed in July 2003, when most of the liberal arts departments from the former College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15] merged with most of the departments from the former College of Human Sciences and Education [RG 19].
  Although the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences (CLAHS) was created in 2003, items dated up to 2015 and later may be found in the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15].
  - RG 48 - College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences (CLAHS) (Information and Publications)
    May include Veterans in Society; Office of VT-Shaped Learning
  - RG 48/1 - Office of the Dean
  - RG 48/2 - Individual Faculty
  - RG 48/3 - School of Communication
    In 1970, the Department of Performing Arts and Communications (PAC) [RG 15/15] formed in the College of Arts and Sciences (CAS) with courses in theatre arts, music, and communications. PAC split into three departments: Music [RG 15/15/2], Theatre Arts [RG 15/15/3], and Communication [RG 15/15/1]. In July 2003, CAS dissolved, and the Department of Communication moved to the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences (CLAHS). The Cinema program developed in the department but later separated and joined the departments of Music and of Theatre Arts as the School of Performing Arts and Cinema [RG 48/7] in 2013. In 2020, the Department of Communication became a school.
    See also RG 15/15; RG 15/15/1.
  - RG 48/4 - Department of English
    Courses in English have been offered since 1872 under different course and department names and organizations: English Language and Literature, 1872-1883; English Language, Literature, and Criticism, 1883-1887; English and Latin, 1887-1891; English, History, and Political Economy, 1891-1898; English, History, and Political Economy, 1891-1898; English, History, and Spanish, 1898-1902; English and Spanish, 1902-1903; English and Political Economy, 1903-1904; English and Economics, 1904-1905; English, 1905-1958; English and Foreign Languages, 1958-1965; and English, 1965-present. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15/10] to the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences in 2003.